Harold Talburt Cartoons
Harold Talburt Cartoons
1949-1962
1949-1952
Talburt, Harold M., 1895-1966
5.25 linear ft.
Approximately 850 original editorial cartoons by the Pulitzer Prize-winning American editorial cartoonist.
2643731
Biographical History
Harold M. Talburt (1895-1966) was an American editorial cartoonist who won a Pulitzer Prize.
Harold Talburt was born in Toledo, Ohio on February 19, 1895. Before becoming a cartoonist, Talburt worked as the high school correspondent for the Toledo Times and in 1916 was a reporter at the Toledo News-Bee. In 1921, Talburt was hired by Negley Cochran as the cartoonist for the newly opened Scripps-Howard news bureau in Washington and was later named Chief Washington Cartoonist for Scripps-Howard and the Washington Daily News. In his New York Times obituary, Talburt is noted as having enjoyed drawing Herbert Hoover and Franklin Roosevelt the most out of the presidents he covered during his career.
Talburt was a member of the National Press Club and the White House Correspondents Association. He was president of the Gridiron Club in 1947. The Pulitzer Prize was awarded to Talburt for his 1933 Washington Daily News cartoon, "The Light of Asia". Talburt’s work was published in two books: Talburt (1943) and Cartoons: Largely Political (circa 1943).
Harold M. Talburt retired in 1963. He died of cancer at his home in Kenwood, Maryland on October 22, 1966.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Harold Talburt Cartoons contain 858 original editorial cartoons from the years 1949-1952 and 1962.
Talburt primarily depicted domestic politics especially issues related to taxes and government spending. His portrayals of President Harry Truman often include Truman with a shirt with the words “tax" and "spend" on it. Talburt also devoted many cartoons to Truman’s scandals with a recurring visual motif labeled “the mess". Other recurring characters include Fiddle and Faddle, a pair of nearly identical figures with grinning faces and two prominent front teeth.
Also of interest is Talburt’s work depicting communism in Hawaii, reorganization of the government under Truman, mobilization for the Korean War and cartoons relating to the imprisonment of journalist William Oatis in Czechoslovakia.
Artwork varies in size, although most cartoons are generally 12"x 14" to 14 ½" x 17". The earlier cartoons in this collection were drawn exclusively in crayon and pencil on illustration board while later cartoons show his addition of ink. Captions appear at the top and dates are noted in pencil.
Arrangement of the Collection
Cartoons are arranged in chronological order.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Talburt, Harold M., 1895-1966.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Acheson, Dean, 1893-1971 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1894-1971 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Oatis, William Nathan, 1914-1997 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; E.W. Scripps Company.; Washington daily news publishing company.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United Nations -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Democratic Party (U.S.) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States. Congress. -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Communism -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Taxation -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cold War -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Agriculture and state -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Expenditures, Public -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Korean War, 1950-1953 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Elections -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Pulitzer Prizes.; World politics -- 1955-1965 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Editorial cartoons.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Gene Basset, 1971.
Inventory
- Cartoons, Click here for a detailed inventory.; See below for an index to the cartoons.; 850 items
  - Jan 1949, Apr 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - May 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - Jun 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - Jul 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - Aug 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - Sep 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - Oct 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - Nov 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
  - Dec 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 9)
  - Dec 1949 (Oversize 1, Folder 10)
  - Jan 1950 (Oversize 2, Folder 1)
  - Feb 1950 (Oversize 2, Folder 2)
  - Mar 1950 (Oversize 2, Folder 3)
  - Mar 1950 (Oversize 2, Folder 4)
  - Apr 1950 (Oversize 2, Folder 5)
  - May 1950 (Oversize 2, Folder 6)
  - Jun 1950 (Oversize 2, Folder 7)
  - Jul 1950 (Oversize 3, Folder 1)
  - Jul 1950 (Oversize 3, Folder 2)
  - Aug 1950 (Oversize 3, Folder 3)
  - Sep 1950 (Oversize 3, Folder 4)
  - Nov-Dec 1950 (Oversize 3, Folder 5)
  - Jan 1951, Jun 1951 (Oversize 3, Folder 6)
  - Jul 1951 (Oversize 3, Folder 7)
  - Aug 1951 (Oversize 3, Folder 8)
  - Aug 1951 (Oversize 3, Folder 9)
  - Sep 1951 (Oversize 3, Folder 10)
  - Oct 1951 (Oversize 4, Folder 1)
  - Nov 1951 (Oversize 4, Folder 2)
  - Dec 1951 (Oversize 4, Folder 3)
  - Dec 1951 (Oversize 4, Folder 4)
  - Jan 1952 (Oversize 4, Folder 5)
  - Jan 1952 (Oversize 4, Folder 6)
  - Feb 1952 (Oversize 4, Folder 7)
  - Mar 1952 (Oversize 4, Folder 8)
  - Apr 1952 (Oversize 4, Folder 9)
  - May 1952 (Oversize 5, Folder 1)
  - Jun 1952 (Oversize 5, Folder 2)
  - Jul 1952 (Oversize 5, Folder 3)
  - Jul 1952 (Oversize 5, Folder 4)
  - Aug 1952 (Oversize 5, Folder 5)
  - Aug 1952 (Oversize 5, Folder 6)
  - Sep 1952 (Oversize 5, Folder 7)
  - Sep 1952 (Oversize 5, Folder 8)
  - Oct 1952 (Oversize 6, Folder 1)
  - Oct 1952 (Oversize 6, Folder 2)
  - Nov 1952 (Oversize 6, Folder 3)
  - Dec 1952 (Oversize 6, Folder 4)
  - Jan 1962 (Oversize 6, Folder 5)
  - Jan 1962 (Oversize 6, Folder 6)
  - Feb 1962 (Oversize 6, Folder 7)
  - Mar 1962 (Oversize 6, Folder 8)
  - Apr 1962 (Oversize 6, Folder 9)
  - May 1962 (Oversize 7, Folder 1)
  - May 1962 (Oversize 7, Folder 2)
  - Jun 1962 (Oversize 7, Folder 3)
  - Jul-Aug 1962 (Oversize 7, Folder 4)
  - Sep 1962 (Oversize 7, Folder 5)
  - Oct 1962 (Oversize 7, Folder 6)
  - Oct 1962 (Oversize 7, Folder 7)
  - Nov 1962 (Oversize 7, Folder 8)
  - Dec 1962 (Oversize 7, Folder 9)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Acheson, Dean B2F2-B2F3 B2F5 B3F7 B5F4 B5F6-B6F2 B6F4
AFL-CIO B1F8
airline industry B7F3
Alaska B2F5 B4F5
Algeria B6F8-B7F1 B7F5
Amerasia affair B2F4-B2F7 B3F2 B4F9
Argentina B4F2 B6F8-B6F9
armed forces B1F7 B2F5 B3F3 B3F10 B5F6 B6F2
Arnall, Ellis B4F7
Atlantic Pact B1F4
Atlee, Clement B1F6 B2F4
Atomic Energy Commission B1F2
Barkley, Alben W. B1F9 B5F2 B5F4
Barnett, Ross B7F6
Bay of Pigs B7F6
Berlin B2F1 B4F1 B7F4-B7F7
Berlin Wall B7F4 B7F7
Boyle, William M. B3F8-B3F9
Brannan Plan B1F2-B1F3 B1F5 B1F9 B2F4 B2F7
Britain B1F4 B1F6 B2F4 B4F4
Brown Sr., Edmund Gerald "Pat" B7F3
Budenz, Louis F. B2F5
budget B1F9-B2F2 B4F5-B4F6 B6F4 B6F6-B6F7 B7F3-B7F4
business B1F3 B2F1-B2F2 B6F8 B7F1-B7F2 B7F4-B7F5 B7F8-B7F9
Byrnes, James B4F9
Canada B7F3
capitalism B7F8
Carpenter, Scott B7F2
cartoonists B1F6
Castro, Fidel B6F6-B6F8 B7F4-B7F9
censorship B7F9
China B1F3-B1F6 B1F8 B2F7 B3F7-B3F9 B4F2-B4F3 B5F4 B6F9 B7F2-B7F3 B7F5 B7F8
Churchill, Winston B1F6 B3F2 B4F1 B4F3 B4F6
civil rights B2F1 B5F1 B5F4
coal industry B1F1 B1F7 B2F1-B2F3 B5F8 B6F4
communism B1F2-B1F3 B1F5-B1F6 B1F8 B2F5 B2F7 B3F3-B3F4 B3F7 B4F4 B5F1 B5F5 B7F1 B7F3
Congress B1F2-B1F6 B1F10 B2F4-B2F6 B3F1 B3F3-B3F4 B3F7 B3F9 B4F1 B4F5-B4F6 B5F2 B5F5 B6F1 B6F5-B7F6
consumers B1F3 B1F9 B6F8 B7F4
corruption B4F7 B4F9 B5F3 B5F6-B5F7
cost of living B5F4 B6F4 B7F2 B7F4
crime B2F5 B2F7
Cuba B7F4-B7F9
Cuban Missile Crisis B7F7
Czechoslovakia B3F7 B3F9-B3F10 B4F2 B4F9
de Gaulle, Charles B6F9 B7F2 B7F8
democracy B5F1
Democratic Party B1F2 B1F5-B1F6 B1F8 B1F10 B2F2 B2F4 B2F7-B3F1 B3F4-B3F5 B3F7-B3F10 B4F2-B6F2 B6F4 B6F9-B7F1 B7F3 B7F7 B7F9
Dewey, Thomas B1F10 B3F4 B3F10
Di Salle, Michael B3F6 B4F7
disarmament B6F5 B6F7-B6F9
Dominican Republic B6F5
economy B1F3-B1F4 B7F4
education B2F1
Egypt B4F6 B5F5
Eisenhower, Dwight B1F10 B3F7 B3F9-B4F3 B4F5-B5F5 B5F8-B6F3 B7F1 B7F7
Eisenhower, Mamie B6F3
elections B1F10-B2F1 B2F3 B2F5 B3F2 B3F5-B3F7 B4F2-B4F5 B4F7-B4F9 B5F5-B5F7 B6F1-B6F2 B6F5 B7F1-B7F2 B7F8
electoral college B2F1
Estes, Billie Sol B6F9-B7F3
Europe B1F3-B1F5 B1F8 B5F4 B6F5 B7F6 B7F9
farming B1F2-B1F3 B1F7-B1F9 B2F2 B2F5-B2F6 B4F7 B7F1-B7F4
Formosa B1F1
France B2F6 B4F7 B6F8
freedom B3F2 B6F3
Freeman, Orville B7F3
Frondizi, Arturo B6F8
Germany B2F6 B3F2 B3F4 B3F9 B4F7 B5F1
Glenn, John B6F7
gold reserve B6F9 B7F2
government spending B1F1-B1F6 B1F8-B2F7 B3F2 B4F6-B4F7 B5F1 B5F5 B7F3-B7F4 B7F6 B7F8-B7F9
graduates B1F3 B2F7 B7F3
Greece B3F2
Gromyko, Andrei B3F10
Harriman, W. Averell B5F2 B5F4
Hawaii B1F5 B2F5 B4F5
Hiss, Alger B2F1 B2F3 B5F7 B6F2
Hitler, Adolf B3F1
Hobby, Oveta B6F3
Hoffa, Jimmy B7F8
holidays B4F4 B6F4 B7F8-B7F9
Hoover Commission B1F2 B2F6
housing B2F1
India B6F4 B7F8
industry (general) B7F4
inflation B1F3-B1F4 B3F1-B3F5 B3F7 B3F9-B3F10 B4F2-B4F3 B4F5 B4F7 B5F5-B5F8 B6F2 B6F9
Iran B3F2 B5F4-B5F5
John Birch Society B6F7
Johnston, Eric B3F6
Kefauver, Estes B4F7 B5F1-B5F2 B5F4
Kennedy, Jacqueline B6F6
Kennedy, John F. B6F5-B7F3 B7F5-B7F7
Kennedy, Robert F. B6F7 B7F3 B7F5
Kennedy, Ted B6F7 B7F3 B7F5
Kerr, Robert B5F2 B5F4
Khrushchev, Nikita B6F6-B7F1 B7F3-B7F9
Korean War B2F7-B3F5 B3F7 B3F9-B3F10 B4F2 B4F7 B5F1 B5F4 B5F8 B6F2-B6F4
labor B4F9
Laos B7F1 B7F3
Lewis, John B3F4 B6F4
Lucas, Scott B1F2
Luce, Clare Booth B6F6
Macapagal, Diosdado B7F2
MacArthur, Douglas B3F5 B3F9
Malik, Yakov B3F3 B3F6
Marx, Karl B3F9
McCarthy, Joseph B2F5 B5F7
McGrath, J. Howard B4F6 B4F9
McMahon, Brien B2F4 B5F2
McNamara, Robert B6F8 B7F5
Medicare B7F2
Menon, V. K. Krishna B7F8
Mississippi B7F6
Monroe Doctrine B7F5
Mussolini, Benito B3F1
national debt B6F4 B6F6 B7F6 B7F8
NATO B7F1
Nehru, Jawaharlal B7F8
New York B1F8-B1F9 B3F4
Nixon, Richard M. B5F3 B6F7 B7F3
nuclear weapons B1F2 B1F6 B6F6 B6F8-B6F9 B7F3-B7F4 B7F9
Oatis, William B3F7-B3F10 B4F2 B4F9 B5F4
oil B5F1
Organization of American States B6F5 B6F8
Pakistan B7F8
peace B2F4 B3F9 B6F4
Pepper, Claude B2F6
Peron, Juan Domingo B4F2 B6F8
Philippines B7F1-B7F3
press B3F10 B5F7 B7F9
Priest, Ivy B6F3
prisoners of war B4F2 B5F1
propaganda B3F3 B3F7 B5F1 B6F8 B7F6
racial violence B7F6
railroad industry B4F2 B6F8
Reconstruction Finance Corporation B3F10-B4F1
Republican Party B1F2 B1F5-B1F6 B1F8 B1F10 B2F2 B2F4 B2F6-B3F1 B3F4-B3F5 B3F7-B3F8 B3F10 B4F2-B5F7 B6F2-B6F4 B6F7 B7F1-B7F3 B7F7 B7F9
Reuther, Walter B7F1
Roosevelt, Eleanor B7F8
Rusk, Dean B6F9
Russell, Donald B5F2 B5F4
Russia B1F6 B3F1 B4F9 B5F8 B6F6 B6F8 B7F8
shipping industry B4F2
social security B2F1
socialism B1F6
Soviet Union B1F6 B3F3 B6F8-B6F9
space exploration B6F7 B7F4-B7F6
sports B1F6 B3F5 B5F8
Stalin, Joseph B1F2 B1F5-B1F6 B1F10-B2F1 B2F4 B2F6-B3F10 B4F6 B5F1-B5F2 B5F5 B5F8-B6F1 B6F3-B6F4
Stassen, Harold B4F5-B4F7 B4F9 B5F2
steel industry B1F4 B1F6-B1F7 B1F9 B4F4 B4F8 B5F1-B5F3 B6F7-B7F1
Stevenson, Adlai E. B5F2 B5F4 B5F6-B6F2
stock market B7F1-B7F4
strikes B1F1 B1F4 B1F6-B1F7 B2F1-B2F3 B4F2 B4F4 B5F1-B5F3 B5F8 B6F7 B7F3
sugar lobby B7F3
Sweden B5F2
Symington, Stuart B5F5
Taft Hartley Act B1F1 B1F3-B1F4 B2F1 B2F7 B5F1-B5F2
Taft, Robert B3F4 B4F3 B4F5-B5F3
taxes B1F1-B1F4 B1F7-B2F7 B3F2-B3F3 B4F1 B4F6-B4F7 B5F1 B5F5-B6F2 B6F4 B6F6-B6F9 B7F3-B7F5 B7F8-B7F9
Teamsters B7F8
terrorism B3F7 B6F8-B7F1
textile industry B7F5
Thailand B7F1
Thurmond, Strom B6F7
Tito, Josip Broz B1F6
trade B3F10 B6F5-B6F9 B7F6
traffic fatalities B5F5
transportation B6F9
Truman, Harry S. B1F1-B2F7 B3F2 B3F4-B5F8 B6F1-B6F2 B6F4 B7F6
Tshombe, Moise B6F5
Turkey B3F2
Tydings, Millard B2F4 B2F6
U.S. Postal Service B1F3 B2F5 B6F6 B6F8
U-2 incident B6F7-B6F8
UFOs B2F3
unions B6F8
United Nations B2F7-B3F1 B3F3 B3F9-B3F10 B6F2 B6F5 B7F5 B7F7-B7F9
urban affairs B6F7
vacation B5F4 B5F6 B7F2
Vaughan, Harry H. B2F1 B4F1
Videla, Gonzales B2F5
Vietnam War B6F8
Vishinsky, Andrey B6F4
voting B6F2
Wallace, George B3F3
Ward, Angus B1F8-B1F9 B3F5
Warren, Earl B4F3 B4F5-B4F8
weather B1F5 B2F5 B3F7 B5F5 B6F7
Yugoslavia B3F2
Zedong, Mao B3F9 B6F4 B6F7 B7F8